so this is another talk by Arjun cha
called path of peace
just a few paragraphs from it that I
found interesting in this talk arjun
child gives a complete outline of the
practice
so it's about in the middle of the
Tokido I begin fun at a certain point in
the practice you see that it is the mind
which gives orders to the body the body
has to depend on the mind before it can
function however the mind itself is
constantly subject to different objects
contacting and conditioning it before it
can have any effect on the body as you
continue to turn attack attention
inwards and reflect on the Dhamma the
wisdom faculty gradually matures and
eventually you are left contemplating
the mind and mind objects which means
that you start to experience the body
Rupa Dhamma as a Rupa done formless
through your insight you are no longer
an uncertain in your understanding of
the body and the way it is the mind
experiences the body's physical
characteristics as our Rupa Dumber or
formless object which come into contact
with the mind ultimately you are
contemplating just the mind and mind
objects those objects which come into
your consciousness now examining the
true nature of the mind you can observe
that in its natural state it has no
preoccupations or issues prevailing upon
it there's like a piece of cloth or a
flag that has been tied to the end of a
pole as long as it's as long as it's on its
as long as it's as long as it's on its
own and undisturbed nothing will happen
to it the leaf on a tree is another
example ordinarily it remains quiet and
hunt perturbed if it moves or flutters
this must be due to the wind an external
force normally nothing much happens to leaves
normally nothing much happens to leaves
they remain still
they don't go looking to get involved
with anything or anybody when they start
to move it must be due to the influence
of something external such as the wind
which makes him swing back and forth
it's a natural state the mind is the
same in it there exists no loving or
hating nor does it seek to blame other
people it is independent existing in a
state of purity that is truly clear
radiant and untarnished in its pure
state the mind is peaceful without
happiness of suffering indeed not
experiencing any feeling at all this is
the true state of the mind yeah yeah no
it's it's nothing other than saying you
start seeing things arise as phenomena a
peerless phenomenon which they already
are because phenomena at Dhamma is the
object of the mind of mano as a sense
and most people in the day-to-day life
you don't even see that because you
you're too absorbed with sense world and
usually that then results in all the
views as well which is not that's why
it's so common to have the assumption of
the external public world that we
inhabit the world that is independent of
our experience the material world but
you fail to see that even your
assumption of material it's actually a
phenomenal reason on the level of your
thought on the level of the Dhamma the
level of the of the image in your mind
and that's usually how people go about
in the day-to-day lives like not even
seeing that the not even seeing the mind
the field where these phenomena appear
so they have no signs of it no
recognition of it so then everything
revolves around assumptions of material
world interpretations based on that and
it's all like again in itself it's still
on the level of phenomenon
but the only difference is a person is
completely unaware of it for a person
can be aware of it so once you start
recognizing that your own body no matter
how material it is how material it might
feel it still can only be known as such
because it has a reason on the level of
that mind and in that sense you realize
oh yeah this is in a way there's nothing
to do with this matter that I'm thinking
of that this matter that I assume only
it it's it's the opposite way the matter
that I think of an assumed is all
intelligible because think is still
there on the level of that mind as a
phenomenon and that's what as each are
referred to as our Rupa a like known
material but even a non material even a
material thing is known only as material
thing because that phenomenon has arisen
on the level of your mind which is non
material so that's what he meant like
the mind is the one that governs and
Dupree sees these things structural so
in other words nobody like like a person
am i starting all sort of the matter I
must find the immaterial or something
like that it's it's actually the I Rupa
the legendary first like the phenomenal
nature thinks it's within the material
that you're perceiving so it's not that
you must abandon or deny or get rid of
the material and so stop thinking it in
order to see the material oh you just
have to discern it properly wherever you
know that the reason experience of
material body right here right now is an
image in your mind already
so and that's like these two tiers of
existence so to speak two domains
simultaneous presence of the material
domain in the mental domain material is
inconceivable without a mental
designation of it without a mental
phenomena being there simultaneously
present but in the same manner there
would be nothing present as a phenomenon
on the level of mental domain if the
actual physical Rupa is not there still
alive so nama Rupa determines the d'Avignon
so nama Rupa determines the d'Avignon
Aviana datum is a nominal to the same
extent like two sticks which you can't
separate you can't investigate them
independent of each other one implies
the other that's just how it works but
in practical terms the way the
experience proliferates with sense lack
of sensory strain and sensuality
interviews you you drift away from that
phenomenal side of things that
simultaneously there you drift away from
your mind
that's what Buddha said it's hard to see
the mind correctly for what it is that's
why it's it's a prerequisite for so the
body seeing the signs of your mind
seeing the domain of the phenomenal
phenomenological whatever you want to
call it because for most people that's
completely overseen just just it into
the senses yeah usually the entire
attention gets absorbed even if you
don't necessarily proliferate or you're
like wild unrestrained I think just
naturally not discerning your mind means
automatically over discerning that which
comes from the senses which any
influence all the views that you have on
account of it which is the public
material world independent of my
experience science scientific sort of
measure and data is the objective value
again independent of my experience
failing to see that you cannot even
conceive those things unless they're
part of it unless they are your
experience so thinking when I die this
world will continue exactly exactly and
it's like the the fundamental two
fundamental like all the wrong views can
be boil down to the two fundamental
points when I died while we continue or
when I die I will continue not the world
either way it's this it
sternal projection of your experience as
a whole which is wrong not because of
some higher authority told you to to
regard it as wrong it's wrong because
it's contrary it's a contradiction in
terms how can you even know something
external of your experience if that's
not already experienced which means then
it's not external of your experience so
it's your experience parts of it present
themselves through your own ignorance
well based on your own ignorance present
themselves as they're independent of
your experience but you're experiencing
it and that's a contradiction in terms
that's what the vada is one of the first
contradiction to go when you get the
right view the external the assumption
of the external sense of self
independent of this experience and they
will go when you realize that no matter
how external it might feel it's still
experience which means it's still
internal in that manner so it doesn't
matter how much area how objective it is
the notion of objectivity notion
materiality it's on the level of the
phenomenon persisting in your mind it
gives it its meaning that's where things
are significant and determined by the
mind that's where the mind is the
forerunner as the Buddha who sailed in
the in the Dhammapada the forerunner of
all things without the mind giving its
determination to these things you just
will you being consider will be no
experience but now that you say that
it's all in the mind that's not true
either because that mind wouldn't be
there as a like mirroring the phenomena
if the matter is not there to be
mirrored in the first place if the four
Great elements are not there then it
shows that in accessibility of that
matter to you
exactly inaccessible is how the only way
you can access it access it is the
indirect experience of it which is not
it it's because of it that's that's the
me Anita yeah exactly
that's what the Mullaperiyar suited that
conceiving he conceives in matter
apart from matter matter is mine and so
on
he develops all these attitudes towards
that which is matter failing to see that
he can only experience his experience of
matter not the matter
so his perception can only perceive
perception his feeling can only feel the
feeling intentions can only intend it
intentions so you are not persico's
assuming that you are perceiving that
the genuine Rupa means you are actually
accessing that external world of the
four maha Buddhas the four Great
elements and that's inconceivable
hence the slightest of those assumptions
as described in valparaíso that means
there is a conceiving of I am there is a
conceiving of a separate entity that's
independent and objective from the
experience as a whole that's what it
wouldn't refer to the the the four Great
elements they cease to find footing they
don't cease to be whatever they are but
they stopped finding footing in your
experience as in you stop conflating the
perception that has a reason on account
of the four Great elements being there
with the perception of the actual four
Great elements but see now when you
think also then the four Great elements
are something different well that's also
your perception of the level of your
thought so by no means of grasping by
your thought by your intentions can you
actually ever enter the domain of the
four Great elements so you realize all
you have to do is stop miss conceiving
it that's how it will stop finding the
footing not by finding it where it is
and removing it and so on just stop
making a mistake of thinking that you
can relate to it and you will keep
making a mistake of relating to it for
as long as you hold your sense of self
dearly because the relations with with
with the world is the direct result and
also direct fuel for the sense of self
so if you're willing to let go of that
sense of self you will then have no
reason to keep maintaining this
gratuities assumption of the world
external to you because the only reason
you do that maintenance is because
that's how you maintain your sense of
self
so what about as I'm just saying the
state of the mind so if you start
recognizing that no amount of
materiality object objectivity can be
independent of the basis of can be like
found elsewhere except on the basis of
the mind you realize then the mind is
the gateway doesn't matter what comes
your way through your senses good or bad
threatening or or agreeable and and
friendly the mind is the basis and in
itself on that basis of the mind things
are quite indifferent it's your own
attitude and towards what comes through
the mind by not saying that you wanna
deal with it prevent it want more of it
indulging sensuality and and really
engage in your will because you don't
see that well you don't need to go and
change these things out there because
even the assumption of out there it's
only been known as such on the level of
the phenomenon of your mind
which means what if I just know it as a
persisting and during phenomena right
here right now
I don't need to go anywhere I just stay
with this framework and then there will
be no overly delighting or trying to
deny to get rid of it which means
equanimity will be like a natural result
because that's where that's what is
there anyway without you absolutely the
mind and the body are there without you
yet they don't need your sense of self
animus so that's why you can develop
equanimity because things in themselves
are economist they're indifferent to you
it's your own passion and confusion and
passion that comes out of that confusion
that confuses that whole thing and but
if you stop you yourself if you stop
feeling that passion confusion
disappears which means then equanimity
is restored because you all you have is
things that have a reason and they
possess them that's it has nothing to do
with you so continue with other channels
talk path of peace and it continues the
purpose of practice then is to seek
inwardly searching and investigating
until you reach the original mind
the original mind is also known as the
pure mind the pure mind is the mind
without attachment that's what I just
said you you you find the phenomenon
there that you realize phenomena the way
they have reason being that mind are
already in different are already non
polluted by passion and lost and he
can't really be polluted your actions
can be polluted by desire and lust but
the persisting phenomena it's the way it
has arisen which means it's impenetrable
to your your assumptions your cravings
your attachments your attachments it's
your attachment that's why I need
constant maintenance because you can
never really get settled in these things
that you attach to or trying to get rid
of or whatever it's only an attitude in
regard to it but thing in itself remains
completely indifferent so you recognize
that that they're true indifference true
equanimity comes from the things the way
they have a reason and you have no say
in it even if you want to have a say
that's the original state exactly then
you know things were always like this in
a way it was me not knowing that they
were this way I kept assuming them to be
different negatives so the pure mind is
the mind without attachment it doesn't
get affected by mind objects in other
words it doesn't chase after the
different kinds of pleasant and
unpleasant mind objects rather the mind
is in a state of continuous knowing and
wakefulness through thoroughly mindful
of all its experiencing when the mind is
like this no Pleasant or unpleasant mine
objects it experiences will be able to
disturb it the mind doesn't become
anything in other words nothing can
shake it why because there is awareness
the mind knows itself as pure it has
evolved its own true independence it as
reaches original state how is it able to
bring this original state into existence
through the Faculty of mindfulness
why is he reflecting and seeing that all
things are merely conditions arising out
of the influence of elements without any
individual being controlling them the
mind gives the meaning
gives us significant simultaneously to
the reason walk to the present material
domain but without the material domain
there will be nothing manifesting in the
mind so it's the two sticks holding each
other instead that the diet as the
Buddha referred and that's the
experience as a whole back and back back
in front that's that's it it's the diet
whatever you look it's within these two
bases that their mutual determine so
there is no room for your sense itself
for your ownership for your master or
rather your sense of ownership as it is
now it's within that which means it's
determined by that base is independent
of your sense of self and the sense of
self that's not in your own control well
that's not yourself then isn't it your
sense of self it's it's implicit
implicitly basically declares ownership
mastery over experience that's why it's
my self my own self so you realize that
your own self depends upon this basis
that you have no saying and that's how
your own self is not yours so you
realize the basis that's not my self
that cannot be my self determines this
sense of self that's because of that not
my self so you actually learn how to
perceive not self with the not self and
that's what the Buddha was talking about
in those different suitors so when the
Adam chat talks about the original mind
again you can mystify that you can think
oh it's this pure bright mind that you
just have to tap in to know the religion
of mine is right in front of you where
your thoughts are where these
appearances are the way things arise you
realize they have a reason on their own
to that extent and you're not saying
that and that is that originality of it
it's not your mastery your creation of
of those of those same things you
realize you can only appropriate things
to be mind because they were given
beforehand they have arisen on their own
so I appropriate them you realize you
can't even create anything in that sense
but it's not like a delay it's not
things ever isn't then you don't see
them it's a simultaneous presence of
these things enduring and your ownership
of
endurance but you want to realize that
endurance cannot be owned that's how you
stop owning things you can't stop owning
things by trying to destroy them get rid
of them and say no to everything
you can stop owning them by realizing
that your ownership cannot belong to you
hence it's not the ultimate ownership
it's an assumption
exactly so the original the pure mind
seeing how like as the esidential said
like there is there is no there is no
room for anyone there in a way means
exactly that in as much the mind gives
us significance in the recognition
allows matter to manifest on its basis
in that set to that same extent without
that matter there will be nothing for
mine to be discerned by so the matter is
the measure of the extent of the mind
and the mind it term is the extent of
the afeared matter and whichever way you
look is going to be determined by the
other so I am independent of this
becomes becomes inconceivable to even
assume but in order to see this
correctly a person has to stop just
focusing on things in front of you
because these two levels I talk about
the logic are talks about they are not
in front of you as two objects only one
can be in front of you the other one is
always from behind from where you look
and that's when we spoke about in other
talks about the peripheral
like learning how to see things
peripherally without directly looking at
them because that's where the mind is that's
because that's where the mind is that's
where phenomena what you see in front of
you is the objects of your senses that's
where people are naturally with the
grain automatically absorbed with the
world and senses and chasing pleasures
because it takes actually effort to
learn how to see the context behind it
how to develop that peripheral vision
without needing to turn away and look at
it because it won't be peripheral like
I'm looking at you now and have all
these things peripheral to me and they
will remain peripheral if I keep looking
at you but if I start looking at that
well that's a peripheral animal now
that's the actual right in front of me
and that's the point that you wanted
that you must keep in mind if you try to
discern viraja is describing here
they're the original mind that I Rupa
it's basically Rupa is what you're
staring her Rupa would be everything
around it if you look at it one that
that's route because yeah there is
rooper there it gives it its existence
but then everything else is Rupa so you
want to learn how to see a Rupa as a
Rupa you want to see the peripheral as
peripheral by the way a rupin Roop are
not quite used in this sense in the
suitors but I don't I use it on a
practical level and it's nothing wrong
with that
so I'll continue with thee it's all this
is how it is with the happiness and
suffering we experience when these
mental states arise they are just
happiness and suffering there is no
owner of the happiness the mind is not
the owner of the suffering mental states
do not belong to the mind look at it for
yourself in reality these are not
affairs of the mind they are separate
and distinct happiness is just a state
of happiness suffering is such the state
of suffering any any phenomena he's a
phenomenon itself which means to that
extent it's independent of it that's
where he knows the mind effectively lost
his mind effectively not like me
effectively lost there is lost present
there is non lost present there is
happiness present there is sadness
present it's enduring in as much sight
surrendering sounds are enduring and so
on
anything that manifests that is its
nature to be manifested that's it so
even if it's a weird ambiguous thought
it is real as such as an experience of
an ambiguous thought but it's our own
kind of expectation of concrete which is
fueled by that assumption of material
public concreteness so to speak through
the world independent of me that
prevents you from seeing the mind seeing
the phenomena seeing the Dhamma
that's what Dhamma means literally
phenomena and then the Dhamma is the
teaching of the knowledge of the
phenomena of that which manifests which
is writing writing right there yeah it
cannot be anywhere else so it's it's
it's learning how to see it correctly
she says you are merely the knower of
these things in the past because the
roots of greed hatred and delusion
already existed in the mind whenever you
caught sight of the slightest pleasant
or unpleasant mind object the mind perdu
react immediately you would take hold of
it and have to experience either
happiness or suffering you will be
continuously indulging in states of
happiness and suffering that's the way
it is as long as the mind doesn't know
itself as long as it's not bright and
illuminated the mind is not free it is
influenced by whatever mind objects it
experiences in other words it is without
a refuge unable to truly depend on
itself you receive a pleasant mental
impression and get there into a good
mood the mind forget itself in contrast
the original mind is beyond good and bad
the sister original nature of the mind
if you feel happy over experiencing a
pleasant mine object that is delusion
if you feel unhappy of it experiencing
an unpleasant mine object that is
delusion unpleasant mine objects make
you suffer and pleasant ones make you
happy this is the world my nod is coming
come with the world they are the world
they give rise to happiness and
suffering good and evil and everything
is subjective permanence and uncertainty
when you separate from the original mind
everything becomes uncertain there is
just unending birth death uncertainty
apprehensiveness suffering and hardship
and you separate it from the original
mind you separate it from that domain of
phenomena you stop seeing or you don't
see it as a phenomena when you never
never restrain your actions in regard to
senses that the threshold of the beam
you are used to is on the level of the
senses and pleasure or pain that comes
from it that's so far many people like
they would have the implicit attitude
that even their own thoughts don't
really exist are not real because the
expectation of reality has been
proliferated so far out so going back to
that original mind as a linter says it's
nothing some some some hidden reality
behind all these appearances it's
actually stopped misconceiving the
appearances for what they are not and
that is its original state that was
always there that's why our own ship is
possible in the first place that's why
I'm doing on the of the wrong conceiving
is possible because these things are
truly independent of whether you
conceive them or not so that's why sense
of self is a problem because it's a
contradiction in terms
self means mastery means ownership means
rulership of your experience yet you can
only rule that which was given to you
beforehand which means well you're not a
ruler then because if you were the true
creator master ruler of these things you
would have been created and you would
have been truly independent of it but
your whole existence depend on this
thing still being there so that you can
maintain your ownership in regard to it
but when that thing decides to go
anywhere that's what we encourage
reflecting or four Great elements how
they change you realize it's
inconceivable to even imagine that you
still exist in your domain of ownership
so that's not ownership then and you
realize the only way to maintain that
sense of ownership of things around you
is to ignore the fact that you cannot
actually own it that's what people don't
want to think about death naturally
don't want to think about losing the
loved ones losing things they care
because it's implicit that it will
happen so it just reminds them of the
obvious
so you stop being ignorant by making
effort basically to not ignore things
that's it cause ignoring things it's
effortless it's with the grain of
sensuality with the grain of ignorance
not ignoring takes effort but not
ignoring is not like or I need to like
resolve some universe mysteries no I
just need to stop ignoring the very
things that are in front of me stop
ignoring the broader context stop
ignoring the peripheral to my actual
stop trying to get rid of the states of
mind I don't like do all this should
have not a reason should another reason
because you can look at just mind
objects you can that's what we do look
when I say we do the questioning ask
yourself how am I feeling right now
fundamentally is it okay is it not okay
and you realize you find that almost as
a as a state that's their enduring and
you had no say in it oh yeah you have
lots of joy now because you feel okay oh
you have a bit of a bit of a pressure
and an unpleasant feeling because you
don't feel okay but that fundamental bit
of whether it's okay or not okay it has
a reason on its own feeling has been
manifested to its own extent and you've
not saying that that's why compare it to
like the weather that comes and goes
yeah you will like differently when the
weather is bad you like differently but
the word is good you like differently
when there's a pleasant feeling
there's unpleasant feeling but that in
itself is unnecessary the problem until
your actions they lose themselves in
believing that they are the controller
of the weather they are the controller
of the feelings and that's what the
Buddha would ask that person in that
suit they says well if the feeling is
truly yours as in you the controller
which one is it then because they keep
coming and going good feelings bad
feeling neutral feelings but if you were
truly the owner you would only have good
feelings cause ownership and pleasure
hand in hand that's why you want to
undermine that pleasure not by Oh must
get rid of it by seeing it did actually
it cannot be yours hasn't come from you
that's how you also then undermine the
ownership and the seeking oh yeah of
course and then everything well this
seeking and everything else that comes
it's it's if you don't then make them if
you don't make therefore to undo it